Guide to the James Steel papers
Oregon Historical Society Research Library
James Steel papers
1864-1985
1864-1909
Oregon Historical Society Research Library
Steel, James, 1835-1913
Mss 2922
2.2 cubic feet 4 document cases
Financial records of an Oregon pioneer and early business leader of Portland, including account books, cash books, financial journals, and a cash journal of the First Congregational Church of Portland.
Collection is open for research.
Acquired July 1991, PO38336.
James Steel was an Oregon pioneer and early business leader in Portland. He traveled overland to Oregon from Iowa in 1862, and served as the president of the Willamette Savings Bank and Merchants National Bank until 1890. He built an electric street railway to Oregon City, served as state bank examiner from 1907 to 1910, and was a deacon emeritus of the First Congregational Church in Portland. He is also credited as one of the founders of Tacoma, Washington. His wife was Mary L. Steel.
The collection consists of James Steel's financial records, including cash books, journals, ledgers, and a household expense ledger. Also included are: a cash book from the First Congregational Church, 1874-1878; articles of incorporation of the Oregon and Washington Fireproofing Company, 1890; data on land claims of the Oregon and California Railroad, 1889-1890; data on Lost Horse land claims, 1867-1869; data regarding the development of Tacoma, Washington; biographical information; and a letter from Ladd and Co. to Mary L. Steel detailing the James Steel estate, 1908.
Steel, James, 1835-1913--Finance, Personal
Businessmen--Oregon--Portland
Portland
financial records
- Letter from Ladd & Co. to Mary L. Steel; letter from E. Kimbark MacColl regarding James Steel, 1908 February 20; 1985 January 16 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Account book, 1884-1900 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Account book, 1905-1909 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Cash journal, 1883-1890 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Cash journal, 1883-1892 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Cash journal, 1891-1895 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Cash journal, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- First Congregational Church (Portland, Or.)--Cash journal, 1874-1878 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Household expense ledger, 1871-1875 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Journal, 1864-1870 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Journal, 1870-1883 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Ledger, 1867-1870 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Ledger, 1871-1890 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Ledger, 1891-1894 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Lost Horse land claims on account with M. M. M. McCarver, L. M. Starr, and James Steele; and data on development of Tacoma, 1867-1869 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Merchants National Bank--James Steel account, 1888-1891 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Oregon and California Railroad Company land claims, 1889-1890 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Oregon and Washington Fireproofing Company--Articles of incorporation, 1890 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Title abstract to property in Richmond Addition, Portland, 1866-1924 (Box 4, Folder 5)